Our planet's
continents are fringed by shallow seas
Rarely more than
200 metres deep
they lie on the
continental shelves
which may stretch
sometimes for hundreds of miles
Before the sea
floor drops into deeper
darker waters
All together
they constitute a
mere eight percent of the world's oceans
But they contain
the vast majority of its marine life
A male humpback
whale sings to attract a mate
The whales have
just returned to their breeding grounds
In the shallow
seas of the tropics
The calf is no
more than a few weeks old
Despite being three metres long and weighing nearly a ton
he is nonetheless vulnerable
But his mother
watches over him
And as he
begins to tire
She supports him
close to the surface
So that he can
breathe more easily
These shallows
around the equator
are excellent nurseries
They're warm， calm
and contain
very few predators
The playful calf
is now drinking500 litres of milk a day
But his
mother must starve
There is nothing
for her to eat here
Like many
tropical shallow seas
these crystal
clear waters are virtually lifeless
They receive
year round sunlight
but they lack the
nutrients essential for the growth of plankton
The mother will
be trapped here for the next five months
until her calf
is strong enough
to make the
journey to the feeding grounds
near the poles
Coral reefs are
oases in a watery desert
Most tropical
shallows are barren
But these coral
havens contain one quarter
Of all the marine
life on our planet
Reefs are the
work of polyps
tiny colonial
animals like minute sea anemones
Yet the Great
Barrier Reef is so big
it can be seen
from the moon
It's actually 2
000 separate reefs
that together
form a barrier
stretching for
over a thousand miles
along Australia'
s north eastern coast
Despite
its vast size
this reef does
not contain the greatest variety
of marine life
on the planet
For that
one must
travel north
to Indonesia
There are
individual reefs in Indonesia
that contain
almost as many kinds of fish
as live in the
whole of the Caribbean
There are also
ten times the number of coral species
Coral thrive
in these waters
With the help of
microscopic plants
algae
That grow within
the tissues of the polyps
And the polyps feed by snaring passing morsels with their tentacles
At night
the algae
are inactive
But then the
polyps put out even more tentacles
So coral
in effect
feeds
around the clock
This wellbalanced alliance
brings benefits
to both polyps and algae
And between them
they turn the
barren seas into rich gardens
The Indonesian
reefs contain such a variety of life
because they lie
at a giant crossroads
This is the
meeting place for different seas
The Indian Ocean
and the Pacific
Here
everything
demands a closer look
On the surface
of this sea fan
there are two
polyps that are not polyps
They're
pygmy seahorses
the world'
s smallest
less than two
centimetres high
They are males
settling a territorial dispute
by headbutting
An electric flash？
No
the display
of a file clam
Perhaps this extraordinary pulsation of the clam's fleshy mantle
is a warning to
frighten away nibbling fish
But no one
really knows
And there are
snakes here too
lots of them
These are
banded sea crets
They lay
their eggs on land
but they hunt
here in the water
They're too slow
to catch fish in a straight chase
So they seek prey
that is hiding in the nooks and crannies of the coral
Their bite is highly venomous and paralyzes their victims
And on this reef
the snakes do
not hunt alone
Schools of yellow
goatfish and trevally
are seeking
similar prey
and they attract
the snake's attention
As one group of
hunters searches the reef
they're
joined by the other
At least 30
snakes have now joined the caravan
The big fish
scare the prey into cracks
And there the
snakes can catch them
And anything
fleeing from the crates
Will swim straight into the mouths of the waiting trevally
There's
nowhere to hide
As the raiders
scour the reef
More and more
snakes join the hunt
This cooperation
between snakes and fish
spectacular
though it is
has only
recently been observed
for it only happens on the most remote reefs in Indonesia
Perhaps such hunting alliances were once a common sight
But today
no more than six
percent of Indonesia's reefs
are in their
pristine state
Beyond the coral
stretches a world of shifting sand
Out there with
nowhere to hide
survival
is not easy
and camouflage
can be crucial
If this
wasn't moving
you might think
it was a shell or a rock
In fact
it's an octopus
A gurnard
its huge pectoral fins disguise its shape
And they can also
help in clearing away sand when searching for food
The jawfish
hides underground
The wonderpus
octopus on the other hand
has such a
powerful bite
That it has a
special warning display
To tell others to
keep out of its way
Here and there
plants
manage to take root
And they're
cropped by green turtles
Seagrasses are the only flowering plants that have managed to grow in the sea
Although they put
out a few ribbonlike leaves
They produce very
extensive networks of fleshy stems
rhizomes
that are
buried in the sand
At their lushiest
they can
transform the seabed
into an
underwater meadow
The largest expanse grows in the shallow waters of Shark Bay
in Western
Australia
These vast aquatic grasslands stretch for 1500 square miles
And like
terrestrial prairies
they support
herds of grazers
dugongs
Dugongs are the
largest herbivores in the sea
They can be three
metres long and weigh half a ton
And they eat
nothing but sea grass
mostly the
fleshy rhizomes
which they
excavate with their mobile lips
A herd can clear
a patch of sea grass the size of a football pitch
in a single day
Food is not evenly distributed in the tropical shallow seas
and it can take
a lot of finding
But bottlenose
dolphins are inquisitive
energetic
and very
intelligent
And they have
discovered a shoal of bait fish
Together
they ride a wave
using it to carry
them into the shallows
And there
it will be easier
to make the catch
In Western
Australia
these dolphins
have taken on an even tougher challenge
The fish have
taken refuge close to the beach
where the water
is only a few centimetres deep
Tail slapping is
a method dolphins often use to stun their prey
But it doesn't
seem to work here
The fish are
tantalisingly close
But they're
still out of reach
So the dolphins
try another technique
Vigorously
pumping their tails
they work
up some speed
And then
they hydroplane
Their momentum carries them right through the shallowest waters
and onto the fish
Now they're in
real danger of being stranded
But fortune
favours the brave
Younger
dolphins lie alongside
watching
But so far only
eight individuals here
Have mastered
this daring technique
Although most
life in tropical waters
is concentrated
around the coral reefs
and the sea
grass meadows
There are some
spectacular exceptions
The desert
of Bahrain
seems a very
unlikely place
to find a crowded
bustling colony of seabirds
But every year
a hundred
thousand cecotrichomines
gather
here to breed
It's swelteringly hot
And only vigorous
panting can prevent the birds from fatal overheating
This hardly seems
a good place to rear young
But at least
there are no landbased predators here
The only source
of trouble is likely to be the neighbours
So each nest is
built just beyond pecking reach
But what
about food？
There's only bare
sand and the warm shallow sea beyond
Neither seem
likely to produce enough nourishment
To support bird
life on this scale
The answer is
blowing in the wind
Sand whipped up
by Shamal's offshore winds
blows into the
seas of the Arabian Gulf
With the grains
come nutrients
which act
as fertiliser
and they
transform the shallow sea
into a rich
fishing ground
So paradoxically
it's the roasted
sands of Arabia
that prevent the
Gulf from being another desert in the sea
The whale calf is
now five months old
He's almost
doubled in size
And his days in
his tropical nursery are coming to an end
It has been a
warm and safe place in which to grow up
But there's
nothing to eat here for his mother
She has been living off her fat reserves for the last eight months
And she's
close to starving
She must leave now
while she still
has enough energy
to guide and
protect her calf
on the long
voyage ahead
All across
the tropics
humpbacks are
heading away from the equator
towards the
rich temperate seas
of both the southern and the northern hemispheres
These are colder
rougher
and more
dangerous waters
Mother and calf
must stay close
They can send sound signals to one another above the roar of the ocean
by slapping
fins on the surface
In winter
the temperate
seas are lashed by violent storms
The turbulence
stirs the water
and draws
nutrients up from the depths
But nutrients
alone cannot support life
There must
also be sunlight
In the spring
as the sun daily
climbs higher in the sky
the algae
start to grow
Blooms the size
of the Amazon rainforest
turn the
seas green
Individually
the algae are tiny
but together
they produce three quarters of all the oxygen in our atmosphere
They're eaten by
an array of bewildering creatures
Salps appear in
the plankton soup
Individuals link
together to form chains
which can
stretch for 15 metres
Pumping water
through their bodies
they strain out
algae and other edible particles
Comb jellies
cruise through the water
They too flourish
in this seasonal soup
And for
short periods
they appear in
astounding numbers
Krill
shrimplike
creatures
By weight
they're the most
abundant animals on the planet
A single swarm
can contain two million tons of them
And that is a
lot of fish food
The shallow temperate seas support the greatest concentrations of fish on our planet
Huge shoals migrate from their overwintering grounds in the depths
To feed in
these rich waters
It's these shoals
that support most of the world's sea mammals
Sealions have all
the agility and speed needed
to collect
what they want
and seemingly
delight in doing so
Dusky dolphin
often in pods
two hundred strong
Work together to
reap the harvest
They break up the
shoals into smaller
more manageable balls
And all the
hunters benefit
By midsummer
the surface
nutrients have all been absorbed
The algae die
and the food
chain collapses
In a few
special places
however
the temperate
seas sustain these levels of life
throughout
the summer
Along the
coast of California
ocean currents carry a constant supply of nutrients up from the depths
to the
surface layers
These upwellings
fertilise forests of giant kelp
that thrive in
the summer sunshine
The algal towers
are as high as a threestorey house
and they can grow
by half a metre a day
Life in the kelp
is as full of
drama as in any other forest
But the cast
is less familiar
An army of sea
urchins is mounting an attack
The urchin plague
strikes at the kelp's holdfasts
Their crucial
attachments to the rock
Whole fasts are
extremely tough
But each urchin
has five teeth
Which are
selfsharpening
And are replaced
every few months
Urchins felled
vast areas of kelp forest
creating clearings known as urchin barrens
Yet
"barrens" is a
poor description
Millions of
invertebrates invade the seabed
The most fearsome
predator here is a giant
The sunflower
starfish is a metre across
With an appetite
for brittle stars
It uses its feet
to taste for prey
When its
actions are speeded up
it becomes clear
that the predator'
s fondness for the brittle stars
is almost matched
by the brittle star's ability
to get out
of the way
Sand dollars
flat sea urchins
cluster
together as a defence
But it doesn't
seem to work against the sunflower starfish
The predator extrudes its stomach and wraps it around its victims
liquifying
their soft parts
Nothing is left
of them except their white skeletons
The Californian
upwellings are seasonal and relatively small
But in
southern Africa
they're so big
they create seas
rich enough to support colonies
of over a
million seals
The Benguela current sweeps along the western coastline of southern Africa
driving nutrientrich waters up to the surface
And then
at the
southern tip of Africa
it meets the
Agulhas current
arriving
from the east
The result：
even richer waters
The seals here
thrive on a diet of fish and squid
In temperate seas
there may actually be more squid than fish
These are
chocca squid
And they lay
their egg capsules
In sandy shallows
bathed by the warmer Agulhas current
Each capsule
contains a hundred tiny squid
Within a few days
they develop
spots of pigment，which
when they're adult
they will use to
communicate with one another
With females
continuing to lay eggs
and males still
preoccupied with repelling rivals
the squid
drop their guard
Stingray
Shorttailed stingray can be up to two metres across
They're the
largest of all the stingrays
and they have
appetites to match
Another predator
is on the prowl
The aptly named
ragged tooth shark
Raggies grow to
three metres long
But they share
these waters with a shark
twice their size
The great white
The largest
predatory fish on the planet
Each dawn
Cape fur seals
leave their colony to go fishing
To reach
the open sea
they must cross a
narrow strip of water
And that is
patrolled by great whites
Each seal is
indeed swimming for its life
The shark
relies on surprise
The great white's
turn of speed is powered by a high metabolism
They only thrive
in cold temperate seas
For only these
waters contain sufficient food necessary
To fuel such a
ravenous predator
As you travel
towards the poles
North or South
The colder stormier seas can become even richer
Midway between
South Africa and the South Pole
Lies the isolated
island of Marion
The island sits
in the infamous Roaring Forties
Where incessant
gale force winds
Draw nutrients
up from the depths
Ensuring plenty
of food for king penguins
The kings are
returning from a threeday fishing trip
With food for
their chicks
But first
they must cross
a crowded beach
Threading their
way between gigantic
and badtempered
elephant seals
The 200，000
penguins breeding here
are testament to
the richness of the fishing
King chicks are
dependent on their mothers for over a year
And this puts a
great deal of pressure on the parents
Being flightless
the returning penguins must cross the open beach on foot
Fur seals that have come to the beach to breathe are waiting for them
Fur seals
normally live on krill
但係呢啲已經有咗，一個唔預期嘅口味
係食脂膶嘅鯨魚
Penguins may be
featherweights by comparison
But they have
razor sharp bills and a feisty character
The seal could
easily lose an eye
The only safe way
to grab a penguin is from behind
And the birds are
well aware of that
Both animals are
clumsy on this terrain
But the penguin
has the more to lose
Made it
Two out of three
penguins survive the seal attacks
and succeed in
reaching their ever hungry chicks
The humpbacks are
nearing the end of their epic journeys
After two months
and thousands of miles
they're
entering the polar seas
both in the
north and the south
In the far north
winter is
over at last
and the ice is
starting to melt
The Ilulissat
Island chain running west from Alaska
is the gateway
to the Bering Sea
With the
retreating ice
rough weather and
ferocious currents stir up these shallow seas
Add sunshine
and the mix is
spectacularly productive
Five million shearwaters have flown almost ten thousand miles from Australia to get here
In all
80 million seabirds come here for the summer
The greatest concentration to be found anywhere on Earth
The humpbacks
have finally arrived
The giant shearwater flocks hunt the krill swarms
Sometimes diving
to depths of 40 metres to reach them
A large humpback
eats three tons of krill a day
The polar
seas in summer
are the most
productive on the planet
And the whales
gorge themselves round the clock
The fat reserves
they lay down now
will keep them
alive during the year to come
But it may not
always be this way
Fish and krill
stocks are declining so rapidly
That spectacles
like this may soon be part of history
Once the mother
and calf have reached their feeding grounds
they will separate
With luck
the calf will
make the epic journey across the oceans
from equator to pole
another 70 times
Cruising back and
forth between the shallow seas
Where life
proliferates so abundantly
on our planet